Daniel Varney Thompson
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Daniel Varney Thompson papers
1848-1979, bulk 1923-1979
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Thompson, Daniel V. (Daniel Varney)
9.6 linear feet
The papers of art conservator and historian, engineer, and professor Daniel Varney Thompson (1902-1980) are dated 1848-1979, with the bulk of the material dated 1923-1979. The collection measures 9.6 linear feet and consists of biographical material, correspondence, subject files, writings, artwork, printed material, and photographs.
Provenance
The Daniel Varney Thompson papers were donated to the Archives of American Art in increments between 1974-1981 by Mr. Thompson and his estate.
Related Material
Also found in the Archives of American Art are oral history interviews conducted with Daniel V. Thompson by Robert Brown, September 25, 1974-November 2, 1976. There are also three letters from Thompson to his sister-in-law Edith Simonds Moore.
Alternative Forms Available
Use of originals requires an appointment.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Daniel Varney Thompson (1902-1980) was an art conservator and historian, professor, engineer, and writer. A noted authority on medieval painting, Varney lived and worked primarily in the Boston area and London.
Daniel Varney Thompson was born in New Jersey in 1902. He was the son of Grace Randall Thompson and Daniel Varney Thompson, Sr., a classics teacher at the Lawrenceville School and later headmaster of Boston Latin School. American composer Randall Thompson was his older brother. Following family tradition, Thompson attended Harvard, earning the A.B. in 1922 and A.M. in 1926, focusing his attention on fine arts, physical chemistry, and literature. Daniel V. Thompson stopped using the designation Jr. after his father's death in 1932.
Between 1922 and 1925 Thompson was employed in the Fogg Museum's laboratory devoted to analyzing art materials for the purposes of detecting forgeries, preserving works of art, and devising methods to aid working artists. During this period, Thompson went to Italy as a Sheldon Fellow in Fine Arts, to learn medieval fresco painting techniques from Edward W. Forbes, Director of the Fogg Museum. He also had an opportunity to study medieval and Renaissance painting techniques with Inicio Federico Joni, and while in Italy began life-long friendships with the Forbes family and Bernard Berenson. Thompson served as a technical advisor to the 1924-1925 Second Harvard China Expedition; he traveled to China by way of India, where he studied wall paintings in caves at Ajanta and Elura and researched newly discovered scrolls.
Daniel Varney Thompson was on the faculty of Yale from 1926-1933, where he taught art history, and tempera painting courses, and laid the foundation for the Department of Fine Arts when Yale became a university in 1932. During his time at Yale, Thompson married Cecile [Cecily] de Luze Simonds.
When The American Council of Learned Societies awarded Thompson a research fellowship for the academic year 1933/34, he returned to Europe and surveyed major libraries for materials concerning the history of technology of the arts. Thompson was then invited to be Professor of the History of Technology at the University of London. He was on the faculty from 1934-1946, and also served as research and technical advisor, developing a laboratory at the Courtauld Institute for analysis of art materials.
During World War II, the Courtauld's laboratory - which had facilities for emission, absorption, and x-ray spectrography - was offered to the Ministry of Aircraft Production. To avoid compromising the University's tax-free status, Thompson formed and served as managing director of Daniel Varney Limited, a private company which leased the premises and equipment. From 1940 to 1945, the company was operated in the name of the Courtauld Institute, employing 200 people in tool making, gauge making, fine mechanisms, and development and production of optics instruments. After the war, Daniel Varney Limited shifted its interests to high vacuum diffusion pumps, gas manipulation, and glassblowing.
Upon returning to the United States in 1947, Thompson settled in the Boston area, becoming a technical consultant. He worked on projects for E-Z Mills, Inc., Sylvania Eloctronics, Comstock & Wescott, Inc., and other corporations. He was chief engineer of Jarrell-Ash Co., 1953-1955, redesigning optical instruments, spectrography, and schlieren systems. Between 1955 and 1957, Thompson served as Vice President of Swett & Sibley, involved with the design and development of optical instruments, scanning spectrometers, and densistometers. He then moved to Avco Corporation, where for the next decade he was a Senior Staff Consultant working on optical design in rocket instrumentation. Thompson retired from his engineering career in 1967.
Daniel V. Thompson wrote and published extensively. Art-related writings include translations and a monograph published by Yale University Press, and numerous articles and reviews. Translations are: Cennino Cennini's Il Libro dell'Arte (3 volumes: Text of Il Libro dell'Arte, 1932; The Craftsman's Handbook, 1933; and The Practice of Tempera Painting, 1936), and An Anonymous Fourteenth Century Treatise (De arte illuminadi) (with his student George Heard Hamilton), 1936. A monograph, The Materials and Techniques of Medieval Painting (foreword by Bernard Berenson) appeared in 1936.
Most of Thompson's scientific and technical writings are unpublished and relate to projects for which he served as a consulting engineer.
Soon after retiring, Thompson began a new career that he continued for the remainder of his life. A serious cook and long-time gardener, he began writing about these topics, producing weekly columns that were published by newspapers from Maine to Chicago and contributing articles to Gourmet, Horticulture, and similar periodicals. Thompson also lectured to garden clubs and judged garden and flower competitions.
Daniel Varney Thompson died on January 4, 1980, following an automobile accident in Malaga, Spain.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of art conservator and historian, professor, engineer, and writer Daniel Varney Thompson (1902-1980) are dated 1848-1979, with the bulk of the material dated 1923-1979. The collection measures 9.6 linear feet and consists of biographical material, correspondence, subject files, writings, artwork, printed material, and photographs.
Biographical information includes certificates and diplomas, passports, and wills. Correspondence documents Daniel Varney Thompson's personal and professional life. Personal correspondence centers heavily on family members including his brother, the composer Randall Thompson. Professional correspondence concerns Thompson's academic career, research, writing, and work as a technical consultant and engineer. Among the correspondents are colleagues from Harvard, Yale, the Courtauld Institute, publishers, and academic and technical journals, in addition to corporate clients.
Subject files are comprised of varying correspondence, printed matter, photographs, notes and writings relating to Thompson's areas of interest. Personal and professional subject files include many relating to his research interests and engineering consulting projects. Of particular interest are numerous letters from Bernard Berenson. There is also correspondence with Belle da Costa Greene, as well as files concerning the Kermes beetle (a source of crimson dyes in the middle ages). Food and gardening subject files reflect Thompson's career as a writer and columnist on these subjects.
Writings consist mainly of manuscripts, drafts, research and miscellaneous notes; also included are diaries, poems, miscellaneous items, and a music score. Daniel Varney Thompson's personal and professional writings include two diaries, poems, and student writings. Most of his extant writings are on art-related topics, science and technology. Among the notes is an index to medieval manuscripts on craftsmanship in major European libraries was compiled by Thompson in 1935. His work on the subject remains unpublished and his notes are extremely valuable since some of the materials noted were lost in World War II. Scientific and technical notebooks, along with various wirings and reports, document projects undertaken as a technical consultant and engineer. The food and gardening writings are extensive and consist of manuscripts and notes for articles and columns, and for a book-length compilation of these writings. Among the writings by other authors are diaries of his mother and wife, and a music score by his brother, Randall Thompson.
Artwork by Daniel Varney Thompson, Mary Sargent McKean, and Henry Winslow consists of drawings, prints, watercolors, a sketchbook, and an oil painting. Printed material includes articles and book reviews by Daniel Varney Thompson, and items about or mentioning him and his family. Also found are articles and books about art, history, medieval studies, science and technology, and food and gardening topics.
Photographs are of artwork, people, places and miscellaneous subjects. Images of people are mainly Thompson and family members.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 7 series.
Series 1: Biographical Information, 1848-1970s (Box 1, OV 11-12; 0.3 linear ft.)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1914-1979 (Boxes 1-3; 2.0 linear ft.)
Series 3: Subject Files, 1925-1979 (Boxes 3-6; 3.0 linear ft.)
Series 4: Writings, 1907-1970s (Boxes 6-9; 2.85 linear ft.)
Series 5: Artwork, 1923-1934 (Box 9, OV 13; 5 folders)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1917-1979 (Box 9; 0.75 linear ft.)
Series 7: Photographs, circa 1900-1972 (Box 10; 0.4 linear ft.)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Courtauld Institute of Art -- Faculty
Subjects-Topical:
Art historians; Conservators; Gardening; Food; Authors --Massachusetts; Engineers -- United States; Kermes (Insect)
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Diaries; Sketchbooks; Oil paintings; Poetry; Drawings; Manuscripts; Musical scores; Watercolors; Notebooks; Prints
Names:
Berenson, Bernard,1865-1959; Thompson, Randall, 1899-1984; Winslow, Henry, b. 1874; Greene, Belle da Costa, 1883-1950; McKean, Mary Sargeant
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Information, 1848-1970s, Series 1:; (Box 1, OV 11-12; 0.3 linear ft.)
  Biographical information includes certificates and diplomas, passports, and wills. The item pre-dating Thompson's birth is a family document: the marriage certificate of Samuel Cogswell and Sarah Williams.
  Other information about the Thompson family is included in Thompson's diaries and those of his mother and wife, found among the writings (Series 4). Some printed material (Series 6) concerns the career of his brother, composer Randall Thompson, and other items mention his wife.
  Biographical information is arranged by record type and chronologically within folders.
  - Awards, 1917-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Notes, 1950s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Certificate (Registered Professional Engineer), 1970, (see also OV 11) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Diploma, (see OV 11) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Driver's License, 1933-1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Employment Applications and Recommendation, 1951-1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Family Document, Marriage Certificate, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Passports (Box 1)
    - Cecile deLuze Simonds Thompson, 1920-1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Daniel Varney Thompson, 1920-1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - John Ireland Thompson, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Selective Service Registration, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Wills and Cemetery Deed, 1967, 1970, (see also: OV 12) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Certificate (Registered Professional Engineer) and Diploma (Harvard University), 1926, 1956 (Box OV 11)
  - Blueprint of Thompson Family Headstone, 1970 (Box OV 12)
- Correspondence, 1914-1979, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-3; 2.0 linear ft.)
  Correspondence documents Daniel Varney Thompson's personal and professional life. Mr. Thompson's brief notes about major correspondents immediately pecede the correspondence. Personal correspondence with friends and family includes many letters exchanged with his wife during their courtship and, later, when absent from home. Among the other family correspondence are a small number of letters from his parents, children, and brother, the composer Randall Thompson. Professional correspondence documents Thompson's academic career, research, and writing, and his later work as a technical consultant and engineer.
  Correspondence concerning Thompson's food and garden writing career and additional personal and professional correspondence is scattered among the Subject Files (Series 3).
  Correspondence is arranged in chronological order.
  - Notes on Correspondents by Daniel V. Thompson, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1914-1938, (23 folders) (Box 1, Folder 14-36)
  - Correspondence, 1939-1973, (22 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-22)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1979, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 3)
    - January - December, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
    - Sunday - Saturday (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Clark, Katharine B. - York, Lewis E. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Unidentified; Illegible (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Subject Files, 1925-1979, Series 3:; (Boxes 3-6; 3.0 linear ft.)
  Subject files contain varying combinations of correspondence, printed material, photographs, notes and writings relating to Thompson's areas of interest.
  The series is arranged into 2 subseries:
  3.1: Personal and Professional, 1925-1979
  3.2: Food and Gardening, 1966-1974
  - Personal and Professional, 1925-1979, 3.1:
    Personal and professional subject files include many relating to engineering consulting projects and research interests. Of particular interest are the files on Bernard Berenson consisting of many letters to Thompson dated 1933-1957 and letters from Nicky Mariano, 1959-1966, and Creighton Giilbert, 1968. All of these items appear on microfilm reel 888. Also of note are a file titled Belle da Costa Greene concerning background information and the circumstances surrounding the death of her adopted son. Extensive correspondence, notes, photographs, and research materials (much photocopied) document Thompson's interest in Kermes beetles, the source of crimson dyes in the Middle Ages.
    - Avco Corporation, 1959-1966 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Berenson, Bernard (includes letters from Nicky Mariano and Creighton Gilbert), 1933-1968, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 10-13)
    - China Expedition, Harvard University, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Consulting Projects (Box 3)
      - Mechanical/Optical Instrument System, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Miscellaneous, 1949-1957, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Schlieren-Shadowgraph System, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Tension Frame TF2, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Wavemeter G79, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Wyckoff Hydrogen Discharge Tube, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Daniel Varney, Ltd., 1945-1972 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Dover Publications, Inc., 1955-1972 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Greene, Belle da Costa, 1943-1971 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Hindu Paintings at Elloru, 1925-1933 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Jarrell-Ash Company, 1952-1955, undated, (5 folders) (Box 3, Folder 25-29)
    - Jones, R. V., 1951-1962 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Kermes Beetles(see also: "Memorial" of the Kermes Group Luncheon) (Box 3)
      - Correspondence and Notes, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - Research Material [including photocopies of material dated 1733], 1984, undated, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 33-35)
    - Leases and Mortgage, 1932-1961 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Lucas, Sam, 1951-1974, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Mariano, Nicky (see: Berenson, Bernard) (Box 4)
    - "Memorial" of the Kermés Group Luncheon, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Sylvania Electric Products, Inc., 1951 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - University of Glasgow, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Food and Gardening, 1966-1974, 3.2:
    Food and gardening subject files document Thompson's career as a writer and columnist on these subjects. Included are extensive files of correspondence with readers, as well as editorial correspondence.
    - Agents, 1970-1973, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - B. P. Singer Features, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Backer, Sally ("Sally's Own Cookbook"), 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Banks, Emily A., 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Book Reviews, 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Boyden, Sarah, 1967-1973 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Chicago Sun-Times, 1968-1973 (see also: Readers - Chicago-Sun Times), (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
    - Dun and Lapham Agents for Writers, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Editor and Publisher, 1967-1971 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Family Circle, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Flower and Garden Magazine (see also: Readers - Flower and Garden Magazine), 1969-1973 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - "Food and Garden Gossip" (column), 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - "Foodmanship" (column), 1969-1979 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Francatelli, Charles Elme (see: "Queen Victoria's Chef") (Box 4)
    - Gloxinia-Gesneriad Society, 1968-1971 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Gourmet (see also: Readers - Gourmet), 1966-1974, undated, (6 folders) (Box 4, Folder 21-26)
    - Greaves, Harry, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Hearthside Press, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Horticulture, 1968-1972, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 29-30)
    - Hubley, Ben, 1968-1971 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Kennedy Special Common Crackers, 1967-1970 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Krech, Inez, 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Melanson, Harold R., 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Morton, Miriam L., 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - North Shore Magazine/Essex County Newspapers, Inc. (see also: Readers - North Shore Magazine), 1966-1973, (5 folders) (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
    - "Pleasures of Food and Garden" (column), 1967 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Possible Clients, 1968-1973, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Press (Binghamton, N.Y.) (see also: Readers - Press (Binghamton, N.Y.), 1969-1972 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Press Herald-Evening Express (Portland, Maine) (see also: Readers - Press Herald-Evening Express, 1968-1973, (5 folders) (Box 5, Folder 9-13)
    - "Queen Victoria's Chef" (The Modern Cook by Charles Elme Francatelli), 1972 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence With Readers (Box 5)
      - Chicago Sun-Times, 1969-1972, (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 15-17)
      - Flower and Garden Magazine, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      - Gourmet, 1969-1972 (Box 5, Folder 19)
      - Miscellaneous, 1968-1974, undated, (4 folders) (Box 5, Folder 20-23)
      - North Shore Magazine, 1968-1971 (Box 5, Folder 24)
      - Press, Binghamton, N.Y., 1969-1971 (Box 5, Folder 25)
      - Press Herald-Evening Express (Portland, Me.), 1968-1972, (5 folders) (Box 5, Folder 26-30)
      - Worcester Telegram (Worcester, Mass.), 1968-1870, (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 31-33)
    - Recipes, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Risley, Dorothy, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Saylor, William R., 1969-1971 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Seeds and Supplies, 1967-1972, (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
    - Speaking Engagements, 1968-1970 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Wilder, Isabel, 1966-1973, (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
    - Wines Internationale, 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Worcester Telegram (Worcester, Mass.) (see also: Readers - Worcester Telegram), 1967-1970 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Yankee, 1969-1973 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Writings, 1907-1970s, Series 4:; (Boxes 6-9; 2.85 linear ft.)
  Writings consist mainly of manuscripts, drafts, research and miscellaneous notes; also included are diaries, poems, miscellaneous items, and a music score. Additional writings by Thompson and other authors are found among the subject files (Series 3).
  The series is arranged as 3 subseries:
  4.1: By Daniel Varney Thompson - Personal and Professional, 1921-1966
  4.2: By Daniel Varney Thompson - Food and Garden, 1960s-1970s
  4.3: By Other Authors, 1907-1967
  - By Daniel Varney Thompson - Personal and Professional, 1921-1966, 4.1:
    The personal and professional writings of Daniel Varney Thompson are on art-related topics, science and technology. An index to medieval manuscripts on craftsmanship in major European libraries was compiled by Thompson in 1935 (2 card files). His work on the subject remains unpublished and his notes are extremely valuable since some of the materials noted were lost in World War II. In addition, there are notes and research materials relating to Thompson's translation work. His scientific and technical notebooks (10 vols.) and various writings and reports document projects undertaken as a technical consultant and engineer from the late 1930s through 1960s. Also extant are two diaries, poems, and student writings.
    - Art Notes, Index to Medieval Manuscripts on Craftsmanship (arranged by library), 1935, (2 card files) (Box 6, Folder 12-13)
    - Art Notes, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Art Writings, 1935-1937, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 15-16)
    - Diary, Trip to India (typescript copy), 1924 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Diary and Address Book, 1933-1934, (1 vol. disbound) (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous Writings, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Poems, 1928-1929, undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Scientific and Technical Notebooks, 1926-1949, (4 folders) (Box 6, Folder 22-25)
    - Scientific and Technical Notebooks, 1950-1957, undated, (6 folders) (Box 7, Folder 1-6)
    - Scientific and Technical Notes, 1956-1966, undated, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 7-8)
    - Scientific and Technical Writings, 1937-1957 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Student Notes (art history graduate courses), 1924-1925, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 10-11)
    - Student Papers (English courses), 1921-1922 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Translation, Diversarium vilium schedula by Theophilus Presbyter, circa 1956 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Translation, Il libro dell'arte by Cennino Cennini, circa 1932 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Translation, Secretum Philosophorum, 1934, (3 folders) (Box 7, Folder 15-17)
    - Translation, Various Writings concerning Red and Purple Dyes from Animal Sources, undated (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - By Daniel Varney Thompson - Food and Garden, 1960s-1970s, 4.2:
    Thompson's food and garden writings consist of manuscripts, drafts and notes for articles and columns, and for a book-length compilation of these writings.
    - Articles and Columns, A-Z, by title, 1960s-1970s, (6 folders) (Box 8, Folder 1-6)
    - Articles and Columns, Untitled, 1960s-1970s, undated, (4 folders) (Box 8, Folder 7-10)
    - Articles and Columns, Fragments, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Book, Good Food, Green Gardens and Red and White Wines, 1970s, (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 12-13)
    - Columns, "Food and Garden Gossip," 1970s, (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 14-15)
    - Columns, "Foodmanship," 1969-1971, undated, (5 folders) (Box 8, Folder 16-20)
    - Columns, "Garden Gossip," 1970s, (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 21-22)
    - Columns, "Pleasures of Food and Garden," 1967 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Columns, "The Second Glass," 1970s (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Columns, Unidentified [possibly "Garden Gossip" or column for Horticulture], 1966 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - By Other Authors, 1907-1967, 4.3:
    Writings by other authors include diaries of Thompson's mother and wife and a music score by his brother, Randall Thompson.
    - Saint-Ange, Mme. E. "introduction" (to a cookbook), undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Thompson, Cecile de Luze. Diary, 1964-1967 (Box 9, Folder 2)